Bruce M. Stave Papers 2003.0054
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Bruce M. Stave Papers
undated, 1895-2006.
2003.0054
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
171.6 Linear feet
The collection contains the professional papers of Professor Bruce M. Stave, Board of Trustees Distinguished Professor of History Emeritus and Director of the Oral History Office at the University of Connecticut. He served as Chair of the Department of History between 1985 and 1994.
Stave, Bruce M.
Biography
Bruce M. Stave is Board of Trustees Distinguished Professor of History Emeritus and Director of the Oral History Office at the University of Connecticut. He served as Chair of the Department of History between 1985 and 1994. In 2003, he held the Harry Jack Gray/ NEH Distinguished Visiting Humanist appointment at the University of Hartford.
He is a past Editor of the Oral History Review and currently serves on its Editorial Board. He is co-General Editor of the Palgrave/Macmillan Studies in Oral History series. His co-authored From the Old Country: An Oral History of European Migration to America was published in the Twayne (Macmillan) Oral History series in 1994 and received the 1995 Homer Babbidge Award from the Association for the Study of Connecticut History and an Award of Merit from the Connecticut League of Historical Societies. The University Press of New England published a paperback edition in 1999. Witnesses to Nuremberg: An Oral History of American Participants at the War Crimes Trials appeared in the same Twayne series in 1998. In 2006, he published Red Brick in the Land of Steady Habits: Creating the University of Connecticut, 1881-2006, a comprehensive institutional history, which won the 2007 Babbidge Award. His article, "Oral History: What It Is & How to Do It," appeared in the Summer 2009 issue of the Hog River Journal.
He is the author or editor of eight other books including five in the field of urban history: The New Deal and the Last Hurrah; Urban Bosses, Machines, and Progressive Reformers; Socialism and the Cities; The Making of Urban History: Historiography Through Oral History; and Modern Industrial Cities: History, Policy, and Survival.
Stave was Associate Editor of the Journal of Urban History between 1976 through 2009; it published more than 25 of his oral history conversations with leading urban historians and practitioners. These dealt with the development of the field in the United States, Great Britain, France, Canada, Australia, Sweden, and the People's Republic of China. Some interviews focused on the bringing of urban history to the public in museums and historical societies. Stave also has served as a member of the Board of Directors of the Urban History Association.
He has been a Fulbright Professor at Peking University in Beijing, People's Republic of China (1984-1985), where he taught American urban history, and where he returned to discuss oral history in December, 1998 and May, 2007. His article on oral history in China has been translated into Chinese and published in that nation. He also held Fulbright awards in New Zealand, Australia, and the Philippines (1977), and in India (1968-1969), as well as lecturing and presenting seminars abroad in Argentina, Canada, Chile, China, Cuba, Cypress, Costa Rica, Greece, Iceland, India (2006), Indonesia, Kenya, Nepal, Poland, South Africa, the United Kingdom, Turkey and Uruguay.
Stave was Acting Connecticut State Historian in 2008. As a consequence, he served on the state's Historic Preservation Council and the Connecticut Commission on Culture and Tourism. In 2008, he was appointed by the Governor to the Connecticut Abraham Lincoln Bicentennial Commission. He is on the Board of the Association for the Study of Connecticut History. He is past President of the New England Historical Association and also of the New England Association of Oral History. He has served as a member of the Connecticut Humanities Council and the New England Foundation of the Humanities. Stave was a Vice President of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences. He was founding President of the Connecticut Coordinating Committee for the Promotion of History and continues to serve on its Board of Directors. He has been a National Endowment for the Humanities Fellow and was a Mellon Pre-doctoral Fellow.
Scope and Content
Professional papers of Bruce M. Stave pertaining to his work in oral history, urban history, university administration, instruction, and professional activities.
Arrangement
The collection has been roughly sorted by preliminary series designations. The series may change as the collection is more thoroughly processed over time.
Series I: Red Brick in the Land of Steady Habits ( undated, 1978-2006 )
Series II: Center for Oral History ( undated, 1966-2002 )
Series III: Department of History ( undated, 1895-2001 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
The following materials are not available for research and the entire box is restricted until it has been reviewed: boxes containing University Senate Files may contain Committee of Three Files, faculty employment records and student records, files, exams, and essays.
Acquisition Information
The collection was transferred to the Archives in several installments beginning in 2003 and donated by Deed of Gift in.
University of Connecticut. Dept. of History.; Administrative Records.; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Correspondence.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Oral Histories.; Oral history.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Publications.; Storrs (Conn.); Syllabi.; Typescripts.; Videocassettes.
- Series I: Red Brick in the Land of Steady Habits, undated, 1978-2006
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 1)
    General note
    Photocopies: Ferguson, DiBiaggio, Waugh.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 2)
    Photocopies: Ferguson, DiBiaggio, Jorgensen, Babbidge.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 3)
    Photocopies: Babbidge, Austin, Jorgensen.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 4)
    Photocopies: Babbidge, Jorgensen.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 22)
    Photocopies: Jorgensen, Waugh.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 23)
    Photocopies: Jorgensen, Waugh, McCracken, Gentry, Works.
  - (Box 26)
    - Research Notes, undated
      Transcripts: Waugh, Gillism
    - Education, Religion, and Recreation Transcripts and Files, undated
    - University of Connecticut Administration Interviews, undated
      includes photos.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 41)
    Photocopies: Jorgensen and Waugh.
  - Research Notes, 1991-1994 (Box 43)
    Photocopies: UConn Advance.
  - Research Notes, 1972-2004 (Box 44)
    Photocopies: Connecticut Daily Campus, Invitation.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 49)
    photocopies: Jorgensen, early years, Hill.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 50)
    Photocopies: Jorgensen, Casteen, Hartley.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 51)
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 52)
    Photocopies: Early presidents, Hill.
  - Footnotes, undated (Box 53)
    chapters 1-4
  - Footnotes, undated (Box 54)
    chapters 5-6
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 56)
    Photocopies: articles
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 59)
    Photocopies: Editorial Board
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 60)
  - (Box 61)
    - Research Notes, undated
      Photocopies: Editorial board, Book Drafts: Chapter 6
    - UConn Traditions Journals.
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 62)
    Photocopies: Waugh, Jorgensen, Fergeson, Babbidge, DiBiaggio
  - Red Brick in the Land of Steady Habits, 2006 (Box 63)
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 64)
    Casteen, Advocate
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 91)
    Photocopies: Casteen
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 96)
    photocopies and newspaper clippings: Casteen and Hartley.
  - (Box 101)
    - Research Notes, 1978
      photocopies and newspaper clipping: presidential search,
    - University of Connecticut Campus and Area Maps., circa 1970s
- Series II: Center for Oral History, undated, 1966-2002
  - (Box 8)
    - OHP--Correspondence, Annual Reports, Newsletters
    - New England Oral History
      correspondence, newsletters 1969-1984, mailings, grants, and contracts,
    - Oral History Files
      essays, transcripts, requests, and newsletters 1985-1994,
    - Unidentified catalogues.
  - (Box 9)
    - South Africa n Workshop, 2000
    - Legislature Project, 1995-1996.
  - (Box 10)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1979-2001
    - Oral History Project Budgets, 1984-1985.
  - Nuremberg Exhibit (Box 11)
    photos and labels on foam backing.
  - (Box 12)
    - Oral History Review Files
    - OHA Pamphlets, 1986-1993
    - Unidentified Documents
    - Oral History Project, Connecticut Workers Files
    - Women in Watercolor Files
    - Vietnam Files
      includes photos on cd
    - Deborah Society Files
    - Contemporary Quilts Calendar.
  - Nuremberg Files and Transcripts (Box 13)
    video and nearly 20 - 3.5 inch floppy disks,
  - Oral History Review - Administrative Files, 1996-1998. (Box 14)
  - (Box 15)
    - Oral History Review - Administrative Files, 1996-1999
    - Essays
    - Articles.
  - (Box 16)
    - Oral History Review - Front Office Files, 1996-1999
    - Essays
    - Newsletters
    - Oral History Project Files
      newspaper clippings, publications, newsletters, surveys
    - Oral History Project, Connecticut Workers.
  - (Box 17)
    - Connecticut Oral History Files
    - Oral History Conference Files
    - Correspondence, 1970-1979
    - Oral History Project Placards.
  - (Box 18)
    - Connecticut Oral History - Annual Reports, 1982-1997
    - Oral History Project - Annual Reports, 1977-1978
    - Oral History Association Files, 1966-1973
      Canada and U.S. Univeristies.
  - (Box 22)
    - China Files, circa 1985
      files, journals, pamphlets, photographs, and books,
    - Urban History Files - U.S. and Canada.
  - (Box 24)
    - Teachers Institute Files, circa 1980
    - Fulbright Association File, 1986
    - Colloqia Files, 1986-1991
    - International Studies Files
    - People of Connecticut Files
    - Financial Records, 1986-1991.
  - (Box 25)
    - Sunbelt Cities - Papers
    - People of Connecticut Files
    - Urban Studies Files
    - University of New England Catalogue.
  - (Box 26)
    - Connecticut Workers Files
    - Oral History Project - Ellis Island Files
  - Nuremberg Files: (Box 29)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, one poster, interviews, drafts, photographs, notes, and records.
  - (Box 36)
    - Urban History Files
    - Oral History Project - Ellis Island Files
    - Oral History Project - People of Connecticut Ethnic Files
    - Oral History Project - Intellectual Autobiographies Files
  - (Box 37)
    - Oral History Project - Annual Review, 1972-1976
    - Oral History Review - Photocopies, 1999
      possible duplicates
    - Oral History Review - Drafts and Correspondence, 1999
    - Oral History Review - Revisions, 1999
    - Oral History Review - Manuscript, 1999.
  - (Box 38)
    This Box Must Be Pulled
    - Nuremberg - Teaching Guide, 1997
    - Oral History Project - Correspondence, Memoranda, and Searches, 1999-2002
    - Oral History Project - Bosnia
      Notes, Correspondence, and Questions
    - Pequot Museum, 1998
      newspaper clippings, photocopies, pamphlets, journal, visitors pass, and mailings
    - Graduate Admission Files
      This box may need to be pulled
    - Oral History Review - Photocopy Winter/Spring 1999 - Referee Files, Correspondence, and Typescripts
    - Student Dissertation, 2000
    - Student Essays and Teacher Commentary
    - Journals
      Civil Affairs and Human Rights
    - Oral History Review - Winter 1997 - Photocopies
  - (Box 39)
    - Oral History Review - Summer/Fall 1999 - Correspondence, Drafts, and Reviews
      photos and photocopies of newspaper clippings
    - Oral History Review Correspondence
      Andrew Dunar
    - Library Records
    - Nuremberg Proofs
    - Witness to Nuremberg, Typescripts, Photocopies, and Correspondence
      Catalogue and some handwritten notes.
  - (Box 40)
    - Oral History Review Files, 1990-1995
    - NEH Application
    - Unidentified Documents
    - Transcription - Margery Ryerson, 1981
      three cassette tapes
    - CT Workers Files
      annual reports, advertisements, and catalogues
    - Oral History Files
      invoices, correspondence, catalogues, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, notes, and photocopies
    - Alfred P. Sloan Foundation
      annual reports, photocopies, correspondence, one 3.5 inch flppy disk.
  - (Box 42)
    - Nuremberg Transcriptions
    - Oral History Association Files
      catalogues, membership lists, correspondence, newspaper clippings, conference information, postcard, mailings, journals, newsletters, notes, photocopies, and ephemera
    - Witness to Nuremberg, Manuscript
      photocopies and galley proof
    - Urban History - Course notes, Files, Pamphlets
      includes student work and newspaper clippings
    - Suburbanization Searches, circa 1994
    - Connecticut Maps.
  - (Box 45)
    - Suburbanization Research Notes and Photocopies
    - CSSC - Charles Tilly Working Papers Series
  - Urban History - Interviews, Correspondence, Bibliographies, circa 1977. (Box 55)
  - (Box 57)
    - Mills and Meadows Photographs
    - Mills and Meadows Negatives and Unused Photographs
    - Connecticut Historical Society, Letter
    - Connecticut Workers - Book
  - Mills and Meadows Photographs (Box 58)
  - undated (Box 63)
    - Publications: Red Brick in the Land of Steady Habits, Oral Histories Last Drift
    - Holocaust Interviews
      includes 1 cassette
    - Oral History Files
      memoranda, manuals, mailing, pamphlets, and files
  - (Box 64)
    - Connecticut Civil Liberties Union Files, circa 1970-1975
      numerous files are damaged by rodents and some dropping may still be present, includes newspaper clippings.
  - (Box 84)
    - Connecticut Women Bar Association Research Notes
    - Oral History Review, 1996
    - Urban History Files.
  - (Box 86)
    - Mills and Meadows, Publication Materials and Research Notes
  - (Box 87)
    - Mills and Meadows, Publication Materials and Research Notes
    - Witness to Nuremberg, Publication Materials and Transcripts.
  - (Box 88)
    - Witness to Nuremberg, Transcripts
  - (Box 116)
    - COH Files, 1997
      ephemera, financial documents, photocopies, typescripts, floppy disk, and reports,
    - Connecticut Women, Bar Association, Research Notes, circa 1996
      files, pamphlets, financial documents, and fliers,
    - OHR Files
      financial documents, ephemera, correspondence, and notes.
  - COH Files, 1996-1997 (Box 120)
    pamphlets, newspaper clippings, notes, correspondence, reports, financial documents, fliers, newsletters, and one book.
  - COH Files, 1996-1997 (Box 121)
  - (Box 122)
    - Witness to Nuremberg Files and Proposal, 1996
      newspaper, catalogue of interviews, notes, correspondence, and pamphlets,
  - (Box 123)
    - Voices of World War II Files and Interviews, circa 2001
      correspondence, and 3.5"floppy disks, includes a small box with loose audio cassettes,3.5" floppy disks, and a cd rom,
  - Voices of World War II Files and Interviews, circa 2001 (Box 126)
    correspondence, audio cassettes, notes, student records, photographs, a cd rom, and photocopies: postcards,
    This Box Must Be Pulled.
  - (Box 127)
    - COH Files, 1994-1999
      correspondence, notes, pamphlets, fliers, memoranda, transcripts, photocopies of articles, postcards, and typescripts,
    - Witness to Nuremberg Files
      newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and photocopies.
  - (Box 129)
    - Voices of World War II Files, circa 2001
      - Student Essays, Journals, and Evaluation Notes
      - Interview Forms and Transcript Evaluations
      - Interview Audio Recordings
        all cassettes in a small box
- Series III: History Department, undated, 1895-2001
  [Includes lectures notes, student papers, AAUP and project files.]
  - History Course Essays and Exams, 1987 (Box 27)
  - (Box 28)
    - Cartoons, Correspondence, and Statementsm
    - History 241 Exams
    - CHC Retreat, 1990
    - Library Aquisition Request, 1988
    - Presidential Inagural Booklets
    - University Publications of America Fliers and Advertisments, 1987-1989
    - UMI Research Collection Price List, 1989-1990.
  - (Box 30)
    - History 232 Essays and Exams, 1992-1993
    - Correspondence, 1987-1989
    - Office Files
    - Faculty Job Market Conditions Files, 1990
      newspaper clippings
    - Department Brochures.
  - (Box 31)
    - History Department Office Files, 1989-1991
    - CETA Grant
    - Oral History Project - Interviewee Lists
    - Urban History Conference, 1977
    - History Syllabi, 1975-1984
    - Connecticut Labor History Files
    - Ethnic Heritage Project
    - Jewish Historical Society.
  - (Box 32)
    - People of Connecticut - Ethnic Grant, 1974-1976
      includes letters, loose notes, and newespaper clippings
    - History Course Files, 1976-1980.
  - AAUP Files, 1986-1990. (Box 33)
  - (Box 34)
    - UConn Restructuring consultants
    - China--Urban history, Correspondence, Exchange Program
    - OHP--Employment applications
    - Ethnic Census ( Connecticut), 1970.
  - (Box 35)
    - OHP Files
    - Accounts
    - Media Files
    - AHA Files
    - University Affairs Files, Reporst, and Booklets
      includes newspaper clippings
    - Alumni Files
    - Babbidge Chair Files
    - Center for Independent Historians Files
    - Photographic Glass Plates, 1895
      at least one is damaged
    - NEH - Regional Humanities Center Files.
  - (Box 36)
    - Committee Files, 1997-1999
    - Newspaper Clippings and Digests
    - AAUP Contract.
  - (Box 46)
    - OHA Files and Pamphlets
    - Sales Catalogue
    - AAUP Files, 1995-1996
      includes newspaper clippings and correspondence
    - Ph.D. Examinations
      this box must be pulled
    - Oral History Files and Reports (Folder 13)
      includes 2 posters.
  - (Box 47)
    - ISCAUH Files
    - AAUP Files, Newsletters, and Correspondence
    - University and History Department Files
  - (Box 48)
    - AAUP Files
    - Student Files - Transcripts, Dissertation Prospectuses, and Course of Studies
    - CT Workers Files and Photocopies
    - Curriculum Vita, 1965-1983
    - Student Exams
  - Department of History Files, 1992-1994 (Box 65)
    pamphlets, correspondence, notes, articles, newspaper clippings, newsletters, reports, magazines, and student essays
  - (Box 66)
    - AAUP Files, 1882-1984, 1990-1992
    - University of Connecticut Articles, 1990
    - ROTC Files
    - Confidential Correspondence
    - International Resource Questionaire.
  - University of Connecticut and AAUP Files, 1980-1990 (Box 67)
    newspaper clippings, correspondence, newsletters, memoranda, minutes, notes, articles, and student essays,
  - History Department Files, circa 1991-1994 (Box 68)
    newspaper clippings, budgets, and staffing
  - (Box 69)
    - Department of History Files, Searches, 1994
      Noether Chair,
    - AAUP Files, 1994-1995
    - Connecticut Workers and Technological Change, Research and Grant.
  - (Box 70)
    - Department of History Files, Searches, 1994
    - AAUP Collective Bargaining Files
    - Urban History Files
      newspaper clipping, publications, cartoon strips, articles, and business cards.
  - (Box 71)
    - Urban History Articles, Essays, Notes
    - CCLU Files, circa 1976-1981
      newspaper clipping, articles, correspondence, agendas, minutes, pamphlets, memoranda, and notes.
    - ACLU Annual Report, 1977
    - ACLU and CCLU newspapers and newsletters, 1971-1981.
  - (Box 72)
    - NECCLU Files, 1976-1981
      newspaper clippings, articles, correspondence, agendas, pamphlets, and notes
    - FBI Freedom of Information Request, 1979
  - (Box 73)
    - CCLU Files, 1973-1974
      Kroch controversy, newspaper clippings, journals, and newspapers
    - NEHA Files
    - AHA Files
    - OAH Files
    - University of Connecticut Faculty Affairs Files, 1989
      performance and tenure review,
  - (Box 74)
    - University of Connecticut Faculty Affairs Files, 1989-1990
      Performance and Tenure Review,
    - Connecticut State Historical Commission Files, 1993
    - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences Files, 1988-1991
      correspondence, newspaper clippings, and pamphlets,
    - Student Files
  - (Box 75)
    - AAUP Files, Contracts, and Agendas, 1993-1994
      newspapers clippings,
    - Student Files, This Box Must Be Pulled.
    - AAUP Files, 1996-1997
      newspapers clippings, pamphlets, reports, correspondence, and agendas.
  - (Box 76)
    - AAUP Files, 1996-1998
      newspapers clippings, pamphlets, financial documents, and correspondence,
    - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences Files, 1993-2001 (Folder 27)
      financial documents, correspondence, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, essays, conference fliers, and membership directories (1993-1994 and 1994-1995),
  - (Box 77)
    - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences Administrative Files, 1996-1997
    - University of Connecticut Faculty Affairs Files, 1996
    - Student Records
      transcripts, essays, examinations, correspondence, and newspaper clippings.
  - (Box 78)
    - Student Records
      transcripts, essays, correspondence.
      This Box Must Be Pulled,
    - FUT Collective Barganing Literature, 1975
    - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences Files, Peter Halvorson
    - UConn Chronicles, 1975
    - UConn Research Foundation, Grant Records, Financial Documents, 1970-1975.
  - (Box 79)
    - Social Science Data Center Files
    - University of Connecticut Fulbright Conference Packet, 1977
    - University of Connecticut and Connecticut Governor's Office Budgets, 1973-1982
    - Unidentified Files
    - University of Connecticut Chronicle, 1977.
  - (Box 80)
    - FUT Collective Bargaining Campaign Literature
      pamphlets, calendars, financial documents, and directories,
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985
    - Sweden Files
      travel documents, correspondence, ephemera, journals, pamphlets, articles, and photocopies,
    - History Department Files
      minutes, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and administrative files.
  - (Box 81)
    - History Department Abstracts and Administrative Files
    - CHC Files, 1988-1989
      staff reports, financial reports, publications, applications, articles, essays, invitations, administrative files, and correspondence.
  - Newspapers Clippings, 1995. (Box 82)
  - (Box 83)
    - Dodd Invitation Files and Photocopies: Articles
      some possible duplicates from other boxes,
    - University of Connecticut Digests, and Newspaper Clippings, 1995-1996
    - United Nations 50th Anniversary Flier
    - Nuremberg 50th Anniversary Packets
    - Presidential Advisory Committee on Diversity and Equity, Minutes, 1995
    - Teaching Institute Pamphlet
    - Holocaust Museum Advertisement
    - New Leader Microfilm, 1934-1936
    - Oral History Interviews, Thomas Sadowski and K.B. Clark, circa 1989
    - Unidentified audio cassette
      one mini-cassette,
    - Projector Slide - Therriault Family Farm House in Canada, circa 1900
      possibly belonging to urban history collection.
  - (Box 85)
    - Charles Tilly Reviews and Pamphlets
    - Process-Devco Report and Research Notes, 1993-1994
    - Lithuania, Pamphlets
    - Tiananmen Square, Research Notes
    - Windham, CT and Capitol Planning Region Map.
  - (Box 86)
    - AAUP Files, 1990-1992